Cromwell is a drama, history, war film directed by Ken Hughes.
Disgusted with the policies of King Charles I, Oliver
Cromwell plans to take his family to the New World.
But on the eve of their departure, Cromwell is drawn into the tangled web of
religion and politics that will result in the English Civil War.
Oliver Cromwell, played by Richard Harris.
King Charles I, played by Alec Guinness.
The Earl of Manchester, played by Robert Morley.
Queen Henrietta Maria, played by Dorothy Tutin.
John Carter, played by Frank Finlay.
Prince Rupert, played by Timothy Dalton.
Cromwell is a 1970 British historical drama film
written and directed by Ken Hughes.
It is based on the life of Oliver Cromwell, who rose to lead the Parliamentary forces during the later years
of the English Civil War and, as Lord Protector, ruled Great Britain and Ireland in the 1650s.
It features an ensemble cast, led by Richard Harris as Cromwell and Alec Guinness as King Charles I, with Robert
Morley as Edward Montagu, 2nd Earl of Manchester and Timothy Dalton as Prince Rupert of the Rhine.
The film received two Oscar nominations during the 43rd Academy Awards held in 1971, winning one for Best Costume
Design by Vittorio Nino Novarese, but also for Best Original Score, composed by Frank Cordell.
It was also nominated for a BAFTA Award for Best Costume Design
and a Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score.
At the 7th Moscow International Film Festival in 1971 it won the award for Best Actor (Richard
Harris), and was nominated for the Golden Prize as Best Picture (Ken Hughes).
The film received negative reviews for its many historical inaccuracies; however, much praise went
to the acting (particularly Harris and Guinness), the score, and the costume design.
The film explores themes of biography, based on true
story, oxford, parliament, religion.
The tone is emotional.